
	<chapter>
		<title><label id="sect:styling"/>Styling Your Documents</title>
		<p>
			For each supported output format, there exists a subfolder	
		<tt>transform/&lt;format&gt;</tt> below the installation folder. Inside this
		folder, the XSL stylesheets with the transformation rules for this target
		format and a style definition file <tt>style.xml</tt> are stored.
		</p>
		<p>
			To modify the style definition for a given target format, create and edit a
		copy of the corresponding <tt>style.xml</tt> file. Then use the <tt><b>-s</b></tt>
		command line switch to point the document processor to the new style file. The
		format and contents of the style definition file differ depending on the output
		format.
		</p>
		<section>
			<title>Editing the CSS-Stylesheet</title>
			<p>
				The central style definition for XHTML is an old-fashioned
			CSS stylesheet, wrapped inside an XML container. For users who have previous
			experience with CSS, most parts of the stylesheet should be straight-forward
			to figure out. The following subsections focus on pointing out the elements
			of the stylesheet concerning the page layout.
			</p>
			<minisection>
				<title>Frontpage and Table of Contents</title>
				<p>
					The document head, carrying for example the title, authors, date of
				publication, publisher and copyright details, is set inside a <tt>div</tt>
				section with the id <color rgb="#881111"><tt><b>#head</b></tt></color>,
				</p>
				<figure align="left" border="yes" id="fig:dochead">
					<caption>The title page header elements.</caption>
					<img src="img/html-doc-head.png" print-width="100%" screen-width="800px"/>
				</figure>
				<p>
					marked with a red outline in figure <ref idref="fig:dochead"/>. The header
				elements themselves are arranged in a table with style class <tt><b>head</b></tt>,
				marked by the blue outline in figure <ref idref="fig:dochead"/>.
				Each element is contained in a separate cell with style class <tt><b>head-<i>element</i></b></tt>,
				e.g. <tt><b>head-title</b></tt>. The subtitle is set in the same cell as the main title, but
				wrapped in an extra <tt>div</tt> with style class <tt><b>subtitle</b></tt>, so that it can
				be styled differently from the main title.
				</p>
				<figure  align="left" border="yes" id="fig:doctoc">
					<caption>The table of contents.</caption>
					<img src="img/html-doc-toc.png" print-width="100%" screen-width="800px"/>
				</figure>
				<p>
					The table of contents (TOC) is contained inside a <tt>div</tt> section with id
				<color rgb="#881111"><tt><b>#toc</b></tt></color>, marked with a red outline in
				figure <ref idref="fig:doctoc"/>. The TOC heading and <qq>list of</qq> headings
				are set in <tt>divs</tt> with style class <tt><b>toc-heading</b></tt> and 
				<tt><b>listof-heading</b></tt>, respectively. The entries in the TOC are <tt>divs</tt>
				with style classes <tt><b>toc-mainitem</b></tt> and <tt><b>toc-subitem</b></tt>, the
				empty elements in between sections have style class <tt><b>toc-spacer</b></tt>.
				The indentation of the TOC entries cannot be influenced through the CSS stylesheet, as
				it is applied dynamically during transformation.
				</p>
			</minisection>
			<minisection>
				<title>Navigation Elements</title>
				<p>
					The top navigation bar is set inside a <tt>div</tt> section with id
				<color rgb="#881111"><tt><b>nav-top</b></tt></color>, which in turns contains
				a table with the same style class name. The table has a cell <tt><b>nav-top-title</b></tt>
				displaying the document title and a cell <tt><b>nav-top-buttons</b></tt> containing
				the navigations buttons.
				</p>
				<figure  align="left" border="yes">
					<caption>The top navigation bar.</caption>
					<img src="img/html-page-top.png" print-width="100%" screen-width="800px"/>
				</figure>
				<p>
					Analogously, the bottom navigation bar consists of a <tt>div</tt> with id
				<color rgb="#"><tt><b>nav-bottom</b></tt></color> containing a table carrying the
				same style class name. This table is split into three cells <tt><b>nav-bottom-left</b></tt>,
				<tt><b>nav-bottom-center</b></tt> and <tt><b>nav-bottom-right</b></tt>. The text labels
				and links to previous, next and superordinate sections (see fig. <ref idref="fig:navbottom"/>)
				are styled in separate <tt>spans</tt> with style classes <tt><b>nav-link-dir</b></tt> and
				<tt><b>nav-link</b></tt>, respectively.
				</p>
				<figure  align="left" border="yes" id="fig:navbottom">
					<caption>The navigation bar at the page bottom.</caption>
					<img src="img/html-page-bottom.png" print-width="100%" screen-width="800px"/>
				</figure>
			</minisection>
			<minisection>
				<title>Glossary and Index</title>
				<figure  align="left" border="yes">
					<caption>The glossary.</caption>
					<img src="img/html-glossary.png" print-width="100%" screen-width="800px"/>
				</figure>
				<figure  align="left" border="yes">
					<caption>A keyword index.</caption>
					<img src="img/html-index.png" print-width="100%" screen-width="800px"/>
				</figure>
			</minisection>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Changing the Look of &latex;-based Output</title>
		</section>
	</chapter>

